Guide to the Sherwin B. Nuland Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sherwin B. Nuland papers
1940-2014
YCAL MSS 1113
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
120.33
(124 boxes)
The Sherwin B. Nuland Papers, which span from 1940 to 2014, contain correspondence, writings, audiovisual materials, electronic media, and other papers related to Sherwin B. Nuland's life and work.
Nuland, Sherwin B., 1930-2014
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 113-120 (Audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 121 (Electronic media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 122 (Patient records): Restricted until 2105. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 123 (Student records): Restricted until 2088. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sarah Nuland, 2016.
2019 acquisition: Gift of Sarah Nuland, 2019.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series: I. Correspondence, 1970-2013. II. Writings, 1970-2014. III. Appearance files, 1970-2014. IV. Subject files, 1950-2009. V. Personal papers, 1940-2009. VI. Audiovisual materials, 1980-1999. VII. Digital media, 1996-2013. VIII. Restricted papers, 1966-2005, IX. 2019 acquisition, 2006-2010.
Sherwin B. Nuland
Sherwin B. "Shep" Nuland (1930-2014) was a surgeon, educator, and author. Born in the Bronx, New York, he received his bachelor's degree from New York University in 1951 and went on to study medicine at Yale University. Nuland graduated from Yale in 1955 and worked as a surgeon at Yale-New Haven hospital from 1962-1992. Nuland was also a clinical professor at Yale, teaching from 1962-1991. Over the course of his career, Dr. Nuland researched the history of medicine and the cultural history of death and suffering. Nuland's research produced numerous magazine articles for publications including" The New Republic," as well as several books including "Doctors: The Biography of Medicine" (1988), "The Uncertain Art" (2008), and his most well-known work, "How We Die," which won the National Book Award in 1994 and was a finalist for the Pulitzer Prize in nonfiction in 1995. Dr. Nuland died of prostate cancer.
Scope and Contents
Writings, correspondence, photographs, research files, family papers, patient records, awards, and other papers by or related to Sherwin Nuland.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 21st century -- Archives; Death -- History -- 20th Century; Death -- History -- 21st century; Medicine -- History -- 20th Century; Medicine -- History -- 21st century; Audiovisual materials; Digital media; Born digital; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 21st century; Surgeons -- United States -- 20th Century; Surgeons -- United States -- 21st century; Nuland, Sherwin B., 1930-2014
- Correspondence, 1970-2013; Series I; 18.08; (19 boxes)
  - Letters regarding How We Die, A-M, circa 1993-1997 (Box 1)
  - Letters regarding How We Die, N-Z, circa 1993-1997 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1993 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2001 (Box 4)
  - Connecticut medicine and hospital files, 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
  - General A-B, 1970s-1990s (Box 6)
  - General C-F, 1970s-1990s (Box 7)
  - General G-K, 1970s-1990s (Box 8)
  - General K-M, 1970s-1990s (Box 9)
  - General M-P, 1970s-1990s (Box 10)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correspondence with Sonny Mehta.
  - General Q-W, 1970s-1990s (Box 11)
  - General X-Z, 1970s-1990s (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1990s (Box 13)
    Also includes galley edited draft of "The Doctors Plague."
  - AAHM, JHM, Beaumont Club, Fulton Fellow, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 14)
  - AAHM, JHM, Beaumont Club, Fulton Fellow, circa 1970s (Box 15)
  - AAHM, JHM, Beaumont Club, Fulton Fellow, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2013 (Box 17)
  - How We Die foreign correspondence and World Economic Forum, circa 1990s (Box 18)
  - Correspondence relating to mailed media, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 19)
- Writings, 1970-2014; Series II; 34.33; (36 boxes)
  - Leonardo Da Vinci, The Plague of Doctors, 1990s-2000s (Box 20)
    Includes drafts, research, and related correspondence.
  - Leonardo Da Vinci, The Plague of Doctors, 1990s-2000s (Box 21)
  - The Project, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - The Project, circa 2000s (Box 23)
  - How We Die typescripts, proofs, and clippings, circa 1993 (Box 24)
  - How We Die correspondence and corrected proofs, circa 1992-1994 (Box 25)
  - How We Die, corrected draft, circa 1994 (Box 26)
  - Final manuscript and galleys for "How We Die," with heart illustration, circa 1995 (Box 27)
  - Notes and articles for "How We Die", circa 1980s-1990s (Box 28)
  - Notes and articles for "How We Die", circa 1980s-1990s (Box 29)
  - Clippings, mostly related to How We Die, circa 1994 (Box 30)
  - Wisdom of the Body, galleys with edits, circa 2000s (Box 31)
  - Writings and notes - Wisdom of the Body, circa 1997 (Box 32)
  - Wisdom of the Body, cover proofs, circa 1997 (Box 33)
  - And His Lovely Wife, circa 1991 (Box 34)
    Includes draftes, notebooks, and other materials.
  - Articles and galleys for "The Mysteries Within", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 35)
  - Articles and galleys for "The Mysteries Within", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 36)
  - Galleys and illustrations for "The Doctors", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 37)
  - Notes and pages for "The Doctors", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 38)
  - Correspondence and drafts relating to Doctors, 1990s-2000s (Box 39)
  - Correspondence and drafts relating to Doctors, 1990s-2000s (Box 40)
  - Notes and articles for "Finding My Name" and "Lost in America", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 41)
  - Notes and articles for "Lost in America", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 42)
  - Face of Mercy drafts and research, circa 1990s (Box 43)
  - Face of Mercy drafts, circa 1990s (Box 44)
  - A Surgeon's Valedictory, circa 1992 (Box 45)
  - Publications--NYRB and Yale Medicine, 1990s-2000s (Box 46)
  - Publications--New York Review of Books, 1990-2005 (Box 47)
  - Publications, 1998-2003 (Box 48)
  - Completed articles, 1990s-2000s (Box 49)
  - Completed articles, 1990s-2000s (Box 50)
  - Aborted projects, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 51)
  - Notes for "Classics" manuscript, 1980s-2000s (Box 52)
  - Rotunda exhibit, circa 1980s-1995 (Box 53)
  - Articles, notes, and manuscripts for Hodgkin and Semmelweis, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 54)
  - Writings and related correspondence, 1990s - 2000s (Box 55)
- Appearance files, 1970-2014; Series III; 15.67; (16 boxes)
  - Nuland talks, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 56)
  - Nuland talks, circa 1970s-2010s (Box 57)
  - Appearances, including How We Die paperback tour, 1994-1995 (Box 58)
  - Appearances, 1996-1998 (Box 59)
  - Appearance files, 1990s (Box 60)
  - Talks, appearances, book tour, and engagements that were turned down, 1990s-2008 (Box 61)
  - Appearance files, 1998-1999 (Box 62)
  - Appearance files, 2000-07-2001-10 (Box 63)
  - TEDMED, 2003- (Box 64)
  - Appearances, 2003-2004 (Box 65)
  - Appearance files, 2002-2004 (Box 66)
  - Notes and correspondence related to appearances, 2000s (Box 67)
  - Appearance files, 2000s (Box 68)
  - Appearance files, 2000s (Box 69)
  - Appearance files, 2000s (Box 70)
  - Appearance files, 2000s (Box 71)
- Subject files, 1950-2009; Series IV; 25.17; (25 boxes)
  - Article reprints and notes, 1990s-2000s (Box 72)
  - Article reprints and notes, 1990s-2000s (Box 73)
  - Article reprints and notes, 1990s-2000s (Box 74)
  - Article reprints and notes, 1990s-2000s (Box 75)
  - Techniques, drugs, etc. - Places, institutions, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 76)
  - Techniques, drugs, etc. - Places, institutions, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 77)
  - Library, healthcare, animal rights information, circa 1990s (Box 78)
  - Abdominal to neurology, 1970s-2000s (Box 79)
    Includes photocopies, print outs, and clippings of journal and magazine articles.
  - Nutrition to wound, 1970s-2000s (Box 80)
  - Altman, Foster, DeBakey, Katz, Greenberg, 1990s-2000s (Box 81)
  - Ethics, 1980s-2000s (Box 82)
  - Ethics and the Humanities in Medicine, 1980s-2000s (Box 83)
  - Subject files, 1950s-2000s (Box 84)
    Subjects include the history of medicine, medical education, the history of science, writing, philosophy, biology, malpractice, infanticide, military medicine, dentistry, Judaica, art, and music.
  - Subject files, 1950s-1970s (Box 85)
  - End of life, Yale, CT medicine, 1980s-2000s (Box 86)
  - Clippings, circa 1990s-2006 (Box 87)
  - Clippings, circa 1990s-2006 (Box 88)
  - Publications - New Republic and New Yorker, 1996-2007 (Box 89)
  - End of Life, CT medicine, 1960s-1990s (Box 90)
    Includes a draft of End of Life.
  - Slides, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 91)
  - Subject files - Wisdom of the Body, circa 1997 (Box 92)
  - History of military medicine, undated (Box 93)
    Photocopied research articles for The Face of Mercy.
  - Subject files - AIDS, cancer, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 94)
  - Subject files - AIDS, cancer, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 95)
  - Calendar, 1988 (Box 96)
- Personal papers, 1940-2009; Series V; 16.17; (16 boxes)
  - Nuland biographical materials, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 97)
    Includes miscellaneous articles by Nuland, reviews of Prozac and How We Die, Nuland's curriculum vitae, and portrait photographs of Nuland.
  - American scholar - NYU, circa 2000s (Box 98)
  - Office files, 1990s-2000s (Box 99)
  - National academies, Yale course, De Bakey, 1980s-2000s (Box 100)
  - Current work, 1990s-2000s (Box 101)
  - Library, healthcare reform, animal rights information, 1990s-2000s (Box 102)
  - New England surgical society, HSR, hospice, imbroglio, 1980s-2000s (Box 103)
  - Office files, 1980s-2000s (Box 104)
  - Student papers, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 105)
  - Student papers, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 106)
  - National Book Award, circa 1994-1995 (Box 107)
    Files relating to winning the National Book Award, includes memorabilia, correspondence and other materiales.
  - American scholar - NYU, circa 2000s (Box 108)
  - American scholar - NYU, circa 2000s (Box 109)
  - Office files, 1990s-2000s (Box 110)
  - Hungary, China, Austria, 1990s-2000s (Box 111)
  - American scholar - NYU, 2000s (Box 112)
- Audiovisual materials, 1980-1999; Series VI; 7.92; (8 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of audiovisual material may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Recordings of Nuland TV appearances, circa 1990s; 13 (Box 113)
  - Recordings of Nuland TV appearances, circa 1990s; 13 (Box 114)
  - Recordings of Nuland TV appearances, circa 1990s; 13 (Box 115)
  - Recordings of Nuland TV appearances, circa 1990s; 13 (Box 116)
  - Recordings of Nuland TV appearances, circa 1990s; 10 (Box 117)
  - Audiobook recording of Doctors: The Biography of Medicine, circa 1988; 4 (Box 117)
  - Recordings of Nuland TV appearances, 1994-1996; 12 (Box 118)
  - Audiocassettes, containing various interviews, circa 1980s-1990s; 54 (Box 119)
  - Leonardo, BBC Science, undated; 3 (Box 120)
  - Nuland demo, rough cut, undated; 1 (Box 120)
  - Saul Benison, Fulton Lecture, 1980; 1 (Box 120)
  - Jeanitte, Marion Gabler, Art Galston, Pete Barker, DeBaker, undated; 6 (Box 120)
- Restricted papers, 1966-2005; Series VIII; 1.5; (2 boxes)
  - Patient records, circa 1966-2005 (Box 122)
    Restricted until 2105. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Student records, circa 2005-2013 (Box 123)
    Includes exams, letters of recommendation, and related correspondence.
    Restricted until 2088. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
- 2019 acquisition, 2006-2010; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Materials maintain the organization present at time of acquisition.
  This accession contains materials including writings, clippings, research notes, and correspondence along with documentation related to Nuland's "Canterbury Tales" project.
  - Writings, clippings, research notes, and correspondence, 2006-2010; 5 folders (Box 124)